Finding Aid for the John J. Bonica Papers Biomed.0118
UCLA Library Special Collections
John J. Bonica papers
1938-1996
UCLA Library Special Collections
Bonica, John J.
Biomed.0118
137 Linear Feet (137 cubic-foot cartons, ten oversize flat boxes, six 3"x5"x12" boxes, one 4"x6"x12" box, seven letter-size document boxes, and one legal-size document box.)
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Folders in Box 135 and ledgers in Box 154 are restricted.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942357443606533
Abbreviations Used in the Container List and Collection
Missing Title
AA The Academy of Anesthesiology
AAAS American Association for the Advancement of Science
AAMC Association of American Medical Colleges
AANA American Association of Nurse Anesthetists
AAPM American Academy of Pain Medicine
AAPMgmt American Academy of Pain Management
AAUP American Association of University Professors
ABA American Board of Anesthesiology
ACA American College of Anesthesiologists
ACCPC American College of Clinical Pharmacology and Chemotherapy
ACP American College of Physicians
ACPA American Chronic Pain Association
ACS American College of Surgeons
ADSA American Dental Society of Anesthesiology
AHA Anesthesia History Association
AMA American Medical Association
AOA Alpha Omega Alpha Honor Medical Society
AORN Association of Operating Room Nurses
APS American Pain Society
ARC Anesthesia Research Center
ARNMD Association for Research in Nervous and Mental Disease
ARNMS Association for Research in Nervous and Mental Disease
ASA American Society of Anesthesiologists
ASCM American Society of Chinese Medicine
ASCPT American Society for Clinical Pharmacology and Therapeutics
ASNS American Society for Neuroscience
ASPET American Society for Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics
ASRA American Society of Regional Anesthesia
AUA Association of University Anesthetists
AUP Associated University Physicians
CCGRC Cancer Control Grant Review Committee
CSA California Society of Anesthesiologists
FAS Federation of American Scientists
FASEB Federation of Societies of Experimental Biology
FHCRC Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center
FSARM Federation of Societies of Anesthesiologists of the Republic of Mexico
GMP General Medical Research Program. Project Committee
HEW Department of Health, Education and Welfare
IARS International Anesthesia Research Society
IASP International Association for the Study of Pain
ICA International College of Anesthesiologists
ICS International College of Surgeons
ICSOG International Correspondence Society of Obstetricians and Gynecologists
IPF International Pain Foundation
ISO International Organization for Standardization
ISP International Symposium on Pain
JJB John J. Bonica
KCMS King County Medical Society
LIU Long Island University
MEND Medical Education for National Defense
MOP Management of Pain
NCCGRC National Cancer Control Grant Review Committee
NCI National Cancer Institute
NIAID National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases
NICHD National Institute of Child Health and Human Development
NIDA National Institute on Drug Abuse
NIDR National Institute of Dental Research
NIGMS National Institute of General Medical Sciences
NIH National Institutes of Health
NINCDS National Institute of Neurological and Communicative Disorders and Stroke
NPF National Pain Foundation
NWSA Northwest Society of Anesthesiologists
NYSSA New York State Society of Anesthesiologists
OAA Obstetric Anesthetists Association
PPOBAA Principles and Practice of Obstetric Analgesia and Anesthesia
SAAC Society of Academic Anesthesia Chairmen
SMA Mexican Society of Anesthesiology
SOAP Society for Obstetric Anesthesia and Perinatology
TGH Tacoma General Hospital
UN United Nations
UW University of Washington
WFSA World Federation of Societies of Anaesthesiologists
WHO World Health Organization
WSSA Washington State Society of Anesthesiologists
Biography
John J. Bonica (1917-1994), called "pain relief's founding father" by Time magazine (11 June 1984), was an academic and clinical anesthesiologist, educator, and founder of the International Association for the Study of Pain.
Bonica was born February 16, 1917, to a prominent family in Filicudi, a small island in Italy. His parents, Antonio and Angela, were middle-class, his father serving both in the Italian army during World War I and as deputy mayor of the island. Despite a comfortable and peaceful existence in Filicudi, Antonio, disturbed by Italy's emerging fascism, decided to move the family to America, and emigrated by himself in 1925. In 1928, the Bonica family joined Antonio in Brooklyn, New York, losing their considerable savings in the process. Antonio died in 1932, leaving John, 15 years old and the only son, to support the family by working several jobs. A collegiate wrestler, Bonica began his most lucrative odd job in 1936: wrestling professionally. He was able to support his family and finance his education through wrestling and working as a carnival "strong man" in the summers, and eventually became light heavyweight champion of the world (1941) under the name Johnny "Bull" Walker. He continued wrestling until 1950, well after he needed the money it brought him. Ironically, the sport that financed Bonica's medical schooling, allowing him to make so many advances in the field of pain management, was ultimately responsible for chronic hip and shoulder pains that resulted in numerous operations and lifelong discomfort.
Bonica's interest in medicine began early, while he was still a boy on Filicudi. He studied pre-medicine at Long Island University and at New York University, from which he graduated in 1938 with a B.S. He was then an honor student for four years at the Marquette University School of Medicine. After receiving his M.D. degree in 1942, he married his long-time fiancée, Emma Louise Baldetti, and began a war-shortened internship and specialty training in anesthesiology at St. Vincent's Hospital in New York City. Immediately upon finishing this training, Bonica was assigned to head the anesthesiology section of Madigan Army Hospital at Fort Lewis, Washington, where he was also in charge of training physicians and nurses in anesthesiology before they were sent overseas.
After the war, in 1947 he went to work as Chief of Anesthesia at Tacoma General Hospital and Pierce County Hospital in Tacoma, Washington, where he co-founded the Washington State Society of Anesthesiologists (WSSA) and helped to found the Northwest Society of Anesthesiologists (NWSA), eventually being elected to the presidency of both societies. At this time he also began work on his 1,500 page monograph The Management of Pain, which was published in 1953 and soon came to be considered the "bible" of pain diagnosis and therapy. Additionally, Bonica was teaching anatomy (from 1948) and anesthesiology (from 1955) at the University of Washington (UW) in Seattle.
In 1960 Bonica decided to leave private practice in Tacoma to accept the Chairmanship of the newly created Department of Anesthesiology at the University of Washington. Shortly after assuming this position, he, along with a nurse and a neurosurgeon, founded the UW Multidisciplinary Pain Clinic, the model for similar clinics throughout the world. He continued as Professor and Chairman of the Department of Anesthesiology until 1977, and as Chairman Emeritus and Professor from 1978-1987. He continued working at UW as Professor and Chairman Emeritus until 1992.
In 1973 he organized an International Symposium on Pain, a six and one-half day program that attracted over 350 scientists and health professionals from 13 countries who represented most of the basic science and clinical disciplines. In addition, Bonica suggested the founding of both an international association devoted to the study of pain and an international multidisciplinary journal. The following year the International Association for the Study of Pain (IASP) was officially founded; its journal, PAIN, was first published in 1975. In 1980, Bonica was elected president of the World Federation of Societies of Anaesthesiologists at its 7th World Congress, held in Hamburg, Germany.
Bonica wrote and edited 41 books, was a collaborator and contributor to 60 other books, and wrote almost 300 scientific articles, two-thirds of which were devoted to pain research and therapy. Bonica's many honors include a degree of Doctor of Medical Science (honoris causa) by the University of Siena, Italy, a Doctor of Science degree from Northwestern University, the Silver Medal by the Swedish Medical Society, the Gold Medal for Neuroscience from the German Neurophysiologic Society, and the Gold Medal from the Italian Algologists. He was elected Honorary Fellow of the Faculty of Anaesthetists of the Royal College of Surgeons, a group that is limited to 20 members worldwide. In 1967 he was made Commander and two years later, Grand Officer of the Knights of the Order of Merit of the Republic of Italy --the latter being the highest award given by the President of the Republic to foreign nationals. More recently, he was made Hereditary Knight in the Noble Order of Cingolo Militare at the rank of Baronet by Prince Cesare d'Altavilla/Napoli/Sicilia.
In 1990 he was honored by Pope John Paul II for his contribution to improve the welfare of people worldwide, and the Pope requested a copy of the second edition of the two-volume The Management of Pain, published that year, for his private library. Bonica considered his greatest honor to be the establishment by the University of Washington of the John and Emma Bonica Endowed Chair for Anesthesiology and Pain Research, which is to remain in perpetuity.
John J. Bonica died on August 15, 1994, following his wife of fifty-two years by just over a month. They are buried in Seattle, and are survived by their four children, Angela, Charlotte, Linda, and John.
Scope and Content
The bulk of the collection pertains to Dr. Bonica's professional activities in the 1960s, 1970s, and 1980s. Early materials in the collection include notes from medical school, circa 1938-1940, and correspondence continues until immediately prior to Bonica's death. Additional post-mortem correspondence by his secretary follows. The collection contains manuscript notes, data, and correspondence; slides from presentations; original publication illustrations; audio and video tape reels; scrapbook items;and some personal and conference photographs. Major subjects covered in the collection include pain and its management, pain clinics, clinical and academic anesthesiology, and obstetric analgesia and anesthesia. Bonica's experience with the foundation of the International Association for the Study of Pain and the American Pain Society, close involvement with the World Federation of Societies of Anaesthesiologists, directorship of the University of Washington's Department of Anesthesiology and Multidisciplinary Pain Clinic, and work as Chief of Anesthesia at Tacoma General Hospital are also reflected in the collection. Frequent correspondents include Thomas Hornbein, John S. McDonald, Patrick D. Wall, and John D. Loeser.
See the detailed series descriptions for further information.
The Bonica papers were processed in 1996-1998 by David C. Gartrell with assistance from Heidi Sandstrom in 1997. The collection is organized into ten major series. Brief descriptions of each series may be found within the table of contents under series description within a scope and content note.
Related Oral History
Pain oral history project volume one. Available at Louise M. Darling Biomedical Library History and Special Collections for the Sciences, UCLA.
Anesthesia, Obstetrical. (MeSH); Anesthesia. (MeSH); Anesthesiology. (MeSH); Pain clinics -- Washington. (MeSH); Pain Clinics. (MeSH); Pain -- therapy. (MeSH); Pain. (MeSH); American Pain Society; Bonica, John J.; Hornbein, Thomas F.; International Association for the Study of Pain.; Loeser, John D. (John David); McDonald, John S.; Tacoma General Hospital.; University of Washington. Department of Anesthesiology; University of Washington. Multidisciplinary Pain Center; Wall, Patrick D.; World Federation of Societies of Anaesthesiologists.
- Correspondence
  Scope and Contents note
  The Correspondence Series follows the general organizational system originated by Dr. Bonica's office, with further detailed arrangement by the collection's processor. The files, when accessioned by UCLA, were loosely divided into both alphabetical and chronological order, with some correspondence duplicated in subject files (personal and foreign correspondence). The chronological subseries includes material from the years 1955-57, 1969-1978, 1980-1994, and posthumous incoming correspondence through 1996, some of which was answered by Julie Baker, Dr. Bonica's secretary. The alphabetical subseries contains material from the years 1961-1966, 1971, and 1975-1990. The subject subseries includes personal correspondence from 1959-1992, foreign correspondence from 1984-1992, personal foreign correspondence from 1974-1981, and incoming correspondence from 1992-1996. (The personal subseries is similar to the general correspondence subseries under the Personal series. The two are separate in order to preserve original order. Any query regarding strictly personal correspondence should include both subseries.) The mail logs subseries is comprised of listings of incoming correspondence from 1974-1977 and 1980-1992. The telephone message log subseries covers the years 1979-1988. In general, Bonica did not retain incoming correspondence, though there are some periods which make exception to this rule, namely, the 1960s and the 1990s. Where incoming correspondence was available, it was kept with Bonica's response, either alphabetically or chronologically, according to its original arrangement.
- Conferences and Travel
  This chronological series of "trip files" details Dr. Bonica's extensive travels to nearly 100 world cities to attend conferences, present papers, or give lectures. The series spans the years 1961-1994. A typical folder will contain such items as an itinerary, conference announcements, maps, menus, sightseeing brochures, lecture manuscripts, and, occasionally, notes on the conference or trip.
- Administration
  This series contains a wide variety of materials from Dr. Bonica's tenure as Chief of Anesthesia at Tacoma General Hospital and Pierce County Hospital in Tacoma, Washington, where he began to work in 1947, as Chairman of the Department of Anesthesiology at the University of Washington in Seattle, Washington, beginning in 1960, and as director of the University of Washington Multidisciplinary Pain Center, beginning in 1978. Materials from Dr. Bonica's clinical practice and work at Tacoma are contained in the Tacoma General Hospital subseries. Materials relating to chairmanship of the UW department and direction of the Pain Center are contained in the University of Washington subseries.
- Societies and Associations
  Dr. Bonica had many institutional and organizational associations, and at many levels. The most important of these was the International Association for the Study of Pain (IASP), of which he was founder and, later, president. He was president of the World Federation of Societies of Anesthesiologists from 1980-1984. He helped to found the American Pain Society, the IASP's American chapter. Some folders contain photographs, as noted in the folder listing.
- PAIN [Journal]
  This series is comprised of articles considered by Bonica in an editorial capacity for publication in PAIN, the journal of the International Association for the Study of Pain. In many cases the article is not included, and the folder contains only correspondence.
- Research
  The research series contains raw data collected by Bonica and other researchers, generally for various anesthesia studies. Also included are some manuscripts, as well as several folders relating to Bonica's evaluation of acupuncture analgesia from around the time of his trip to China in the early 1970s. Some materials in this series are restricted; they are noted at the end of the container list.
- Drug Companies
  This series, organized alphabetically by company name, includes correspondence between Bonica and pharmaceutical manufacturers and researchers, reports on drugs, and papers written for drug houses.
- Personal
  Medical/Legal/Financial. These papers include some of the Bonicas' personal records regarding health, law, and finances.
  Writing/Consulting. This subseries contains correspondence and schedules relating to writing commitments; book, article and grant proposal reviews; et cetera.
  Early notes. These are medical school notes from 1938-1940, and attest to Dr. Bonica's commitment to the study of medicine by illustrating his attentiveness, completeness, and often detailed artistic rendering of cells and tissues.
  Family. This subseries is mainly correspondence between Dr. Bonica and members of his family.
  Interests and miscellaneous. Dr. Bonica's interest were wide, and encompassed such varied fields as music and the opera, anti-terrorism, keeping up with old school and wrestling buddies, and his Catholic faith.
  Work-related. This subseries contains such employment related personal issues as leave requests, salary, et cetera.
  Scrapbook. These files contain the many magazine articles, newspaper clippings, awards, press releases and photographs pertaining to Dr. Bonica, who always sought publicity for the pain field in order to draw attention to this "disease state of major national importance."
  Requests for information/action. As a well-known expert on the subject of pain, Dr. Bonica received many queries and requests, for everything from the source of a particular citation, to his opinion on a particular drug's legal status in a pharmacopoeia.
  Biographical. These files represent Dr. Bonica's evolving curriculum vitae, autobiographical statement, summary of research, departmental history, and information sent to various "who's who" publications.
  Bonica chair. From the mid-to late-1980s, Dr. Bonica was involved in the fund raising for the John and Emma Bonica Endowed Chair for Anesthesiology and Pain Research.
  General correspondence. This subseries is similar to the personal correspondence subseries under Correspondence. The two are separate in order to preserve original order. Any query regarding strictly personal correspondence should include both subseries.
  Pocket calendars. These monthly 3" X 5" calendars were prepared for Dr. Bonica by his secretarial staff, and cover the years 1969-1992. Any breaks are noted in the individual box listing.
- Publications
  Bonica wrote and edited many different chapters, articles, and monographs during his professional career. The Publications Series contains manuscripts, illustrations, slides, correspondence, notes and reprints from these publications. Bonica's two major publications, which also are the most heavily represented in the collection, are The Management of Pain, and Principles and Practice of Obstetric Analgesia and Anesthesia, both of which had two editions. A separate subseries for each of these works was created. The Publications, Other subseries represents other important works, while Publications, Miscellaneous includes minor manuscript materials, such as short book chapters or individual papers that were found outside the Manuscripts subseries. Bonica's office maintained a list of his other papers and book chapters from 1977 forward in the form of a manuscript file, which comprises the Manuscripts subseries. Curriculum Vitae Items is a reprints file maintained by Bonica's office.
- Lectures
  This series contains materials used by Bonica in his lectures: manuscripts, printouts of overhead slides, the actual slides in inert polypropylene sleeves, and slide negatives.
- Correspondence
  - Alphabetical
    - A, Misc.: A-Alvarez. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - A, Misc.: Amano-Azzoppardi. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Aagard, George, 1964 - 1990. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Abe, Naotoshi, 1978 - 1980. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Abouleish, Ezzat, 1975 - 1988. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Acquaviva-Shulman, Leslie, 1989. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Adams-Ray, Jack, 1962 - 1971. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Addison, Robert G., 1975 - 1990. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Adriani, John, 1962 - 1979. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Agosti, Luis, 1962 - 1984. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Akamatsu, Toshio, 1965 - 1986. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Albe-Fessard, Denise, 1975 - 1980. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Albright, George A., 1986 - 1986. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Alderman, Marvin, 1975 - 1976. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Alexander, Kathey, 1987 - 1990. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Allen, Gerald D., 1962 - 1975. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Alliata, Yana, Princess, 1975 - 1989. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Alling, Charles C., 1975 - 1981. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Allison, Jean, 1983 - 1985. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Almquist, Edward E., 1976 - 1986. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Alper, Milton H., 1975 - 1988. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Ambrozy, George, 1984 - 1985. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Ament, Richard, 1975 - 1984. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Amundson, David, 1987 - 1989. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Andersson, Sven, 1975 - 1987. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Andes, John, 1962 - 1986. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Ansell, Julian, 1971 - 1986. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Araujo, Manuel Silva, 1971. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Arje, Sydney L., 1962 - 1977. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Aronoff, Gerald M., 1981 - 1987. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Aronski, Antoni, 1978 - 1979. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Augstkalns, Ilze, 1975 - 1976. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Ayim, E. N., 1976 - 1985. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - B, Misc.: Backup-Bayley. (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - B, Misc.: Beach-Bizaillon. (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - B, Misc.: Blab-Bozza. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - B, Misc.: Brachman-Byrd. (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Ballinger, Carter M., 1961 - 1980. (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Bankowski, Zbigniew, 1976 - 1983. (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Barber, Joseph, 1978 - 1990. (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Barretto, Cleomenes, 1976 - 1982. (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Barry, Ben J., 1976 - 1984. (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Barsa, John E., 1975 - 1987. (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Basbaum, Allan, 1983 - 1991. (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Baskett, Peter J. F., 1979 - 1986. (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Battista, Raffaele F., 1982 - 1986. (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Beales, Gerald, 1977 - 1978. (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Beckett, Arnold H., 1971. (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Beecher, Henry K., 1971 - 1976. (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Beeson, Paul B., 1982 - 1983. (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Beghe, Raoul, 1961 - 1978. (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Bellucci, Gualtiero, 1971 - 1984. (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Bendixen, Henrik, 1966 - 1986. (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Benedetti, Constantino, 1977 - 1990. (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Bentcliff, Georgina, 1989. (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Bentley, Lawrence, 1987 - 1989. (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Berger, Philip A., 1983 - 1986. (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Berges, Peter U., 1971 - 1976. (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Berry, Roger J., 1985 - 1990. (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Bertelli, Aldo, 1985 - 1990. (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Besson, Jean-Marie, 1979 - 1990. (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Beswick, Frances, 1976 - 1977. (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Betcher, Albert M., 1961 - 1984. (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Biebuyck, Julian F., 1971 - 1983. (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Bigos, Stanley, 1984 - 1988. (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Bird, Forrest, 1962 - 1987. (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Birkhahn, Jesmond, 1975 - 1980. (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Bitterman, M. E., 1971 - 1975. (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Björlin, Per, 1978 - 1979. (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Black, Emilie A., 1971 - 1983. (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Black, Richard G., 1971 - 1978. (Box 1, Folder 71)